oh yes my friends it's time we finally
start talking about endurance all of us
love a good cardio kickboxing session
where we leave a pile of sweat on the
floor or maybe a prowler session you
prefer where you get a little bit of
prowler flu and lose your lunch on the
floor
a lot of us enjoy or at least attempt to
subject ourselves to a little bit of
endurance or fatigue or conditioning
training but few of us really understand
it from a physiological perspective if
we do it Stanley - silo'd we don't
understand the full breadth of
physiology of endurance now this is a
five-minute video so I'll keep this very
brief in short if you like this topic
though I'll encourage you to check out
the other five 25 and 55 minute videos
of fatigue endurance conditioning
metabolism and all hosts of different
things but let's jump right into it we
have to take this from the entire system
down approach and if we understand human
movement we realize this starts at
number one the nervous system and it
works ourselves all the way down to the
lung so I don't have time to go through
each one of these in depth but basically
what happens is I've listed on the side
there some of the more potent culprits
of fatigue in each of these individual
systems so I'll go through a couple of
them starting with nerves so you get the
idea so we have to realize that our
nervous system itself is actually
powered by and carbohydrate no that's
right we have to generate energy for the
nerves to work if they start losing
their fuel source
they don't contract or prisoner they
don't attract males transmit signals
very well they get fatigued just like a
muscle can in particular one of the
things that's important there is the na+
a sodium pump you can look more to that
if you like that physiology as well as
the pH so any disruptions in any of
those three areas can cause fatigue of
the nervous system whether that be
central or peripheral we can see we
could go through the same thing with the
muscle PCR phosphor creatine a huge
energy source glycogen and fat so those
would all be substrate so those are
things we use to generate energy
metabolic speed is another thing so
sometimes it's not necessarily that
you're fatigued it's just the fact you
can't produce ATP fast enough and that
could be because you lack the enzymes or
whole host of other metal
like reasons or because of pH now
remember pH is a little bit funky
because a lower pH means a higher
fatigue right and so you feel the burn
right you're doing intervals you felt
that before from the blood perspective
same thing it's it's primarily job just
to keep blood glucose levels fairly
stabilized because our brain uses a
whole host of that for fuel and so if
blood glucose levels get too low you can
get fatigued same thing with fat or
we're using the blood to get oxygen in
carbon dioxide out la- is lactate so
we're trying to transport that around
through or other hydrogen protons the H+
getting that out of the overloaded
muscle if that's the case capillary
density and blood flow is gonna be the
primary determinant of things like
eating nutrients and supplies into the
tissue and so one of the classic
adaptations so endurance training is you
increase capitalization to the fibers
and this is why that improves
performance or reduces fatigue
mitochondria density would fall on the
same line here the liver primary job in
terms of exercise performance this is
supply glucose to the muscle and
probably more approximately to the blood
so muscle will eventually take glucose
from the blood therefore reducing blood
glucose so the liver will then kick out
its glycogen into the blood to keep
glucose at a stable level if that runs
out we start becoming fatigued from the
hearts perspective of course we're
trying to circulate blood so that we can
take all the things that are put in all
those byproducts and waste products into
the blood and help get them out via
respiration for the most part and so a
reduction in stroke volume it's the
amount of blood pumped out perc per beat
or the heart rate nice amount of beats
per minute all those things are going to
be limiting factors to performance or
contribute to fatigue and then finally
the lungs of course we're trying to
inhale and otwo in exhale co2 and that's
an active process of maximal exercises
so the the inspiratory lung muscles the
diaphragm and the intercostal muscles
themselves can get fatigued because
remember they are skeletal muscle as
well and so they're gonna run into the
same problems at your normal muscle
weight so that's a quick overview of
fatigue physiology
but let's remember each type of
endurance and we'll talk about a whole
host of different kinds in other videos
has a specific failure point someone
between 1 and 6 in fact several types of
fatigue have multiple so as a little bit
of a teaser you can see this in some of
the other videos I've gone through
several different types of performance
everything from max power to muscular
endurance to intervals along duration
and in those videos I'll explain to you
of these six different levels which one
of these things are fatigued during each
type of activity and then maybe maybe
few nice I'll give you some tips on how
to prevent that from happening but for
now
that's all you get thanks a lot for
second by five minute physiology and
we'll catch up
[Music]
you